A Guide to the Kathleen Cruise Architectural Papers, 1964-1995
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Kathleen Cruise Architectural Papers 1964-1995
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1999-001
8 boxes, 1 oversize folder; 8.0 cu. ft.
The Kathleen Cruise Architectural Papers concentrate on her work for Pacific Gas and Electric Company (PG&E) in San Francisco, 1964-1995.
Kathleen Cruise
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Kathleen Cruise Architectural Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1999.
Biographical Information
Kathleen Cruise is an architect and general contractor in San Francisco, California. She earned an MBA from Golden Gate University (1982), and a Bachelor of Architecture from Virgina Polytechnic Institute and State University, (1970). She is an opinion-leading expert in sustainable approaches to the built environment with a specialization in energy. Kathleen has over 35 years of successful accomplishments with a track record of balancing environmental responsibility with sound business practices. She achieves outstanding results in all phases of facilities management from award winning design to expert real estate management. Representative projects include: PG&E's Energy Center; East Geysers Administration Center, Golden Gate Regional Headquarters and the San Rafael, Garberville and Geyserville Service Centers. Cruise was a loaned executive from PG&E to the Department of Energy for the Greening of the White House Project; Manager of Utilities for Stanford University; Principal, Program Development for Proven Alternatives; Program Manager, Real Estate and Facilities with the Microsoft Corporation and is currently Director of Facilities Management at Fort Mason in San Francisco.
Scope and Content
The Kathleen Cruise Architectural Papers concentrate on her work for Pacific Gas and Electric Company (PG&E) in San Francisco, 1964-1995.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically with the undated material last.
Contents List
- Letters to Mr. Edward Reynolds about the high energy accelerator, 1964. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Cruise's early work, 1964-70. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Specifications for the hospital building at the San Francisco Medical Center (folder 1 of 2), 1970. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Specifications for the hospital building at the San Francisco Medical Center (folder 2 of 2), 1970. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Work for a thesis on surfboard factory design, 1970. (Box-folder 1:5)
- List of inspector special reports, 1971-74. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Inspector special reports for the San Francisco Medical Center, 1972-73. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Jansen House project, 1975. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Miscellaneous notes by Cruise, 1976. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Specifications for alterations of the Junior Academy and Docent Offices of the California Academy of Sciences, 1977. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Information about the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices alterations, 1977-78. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Ceiling drawing for the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices, 1978. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Inspector's special reports for the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices, 1978. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Inspection memos for the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices (folder 1 of 2), 1978. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Inspection memos for the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices (folder 2 of 2), 1978. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Sheet metal submittal literature for the California Academy of Sciences Junior Academy and Docent Offices, 1978. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Motor vessel Santa Rosa renovation project, 1978. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Cruise's appointment book, 1978. (Box-folder 1:18)
- Project manual for the Santa Rosa ferryboat restoration, reconstruction, and renovation, 1979. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Certificate of membership of the Coonstruction Specifications Institute and a copy of their code of ethics, 1979. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Programming workbook-Shasta Division, 1979. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Department of Engineering Research-San Ramon-Pacific Gas and Electric Company, 1979-80. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Slides, photos, and descriptions of the Energy Expo-Pacific Gas and Electric Company, 1980. (Box-folder 2:4)
- North Bay Division, Marin District--master plan study, 1980. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Revised Cascade District consolidation study, 1980. (Box-folder 2:6)
- San Rafael service center site--photos and negatives, 1980. (Box-folder 2:7)
- San Francisco service center--photos and negatives, 1980. (Box-folder 2:8)
- Specifications for structural strengthening in the Humbolt division office building, 1980. (Box-folder 2:9)
- Pacific Gas and Electric company documents, 1980-81. (Box-folder 2:10)
- Photos of Lake Port service center, 1981. (Box-folder 2:11)
- Blueprint reading training course taught by Cruise, 1981. (Box-folder 2:12)
- Slides of storage unit remodeling, 1981. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Coursework for a writing clinic--San Francisco, California, 1981. (Box-folder 2:14)
- Master plan study for the San Francisco division of Pacific Gas and Electric, 1981. (Box-folder 2:15)
- Final grades for MBA courses at Golden Gate University, 1981. (Box-folder 2:16)
- North Bay division Healdsburg service center study, 1981. (Box-folder 2:17)
- Specifications for construction of the Cascade district office, 1981. (Box-folder 2:18)
- Specifications for construction of the Cascade district office (revision 1), 1981. (Box-folder 2:19)
- Sugar house--photos and negatives, 1981. (Box-folder 2:20)
- Slides of Cascade district office, 1981-83. (Box-folder 2:21)
- Paper written by Cruise for EM 205, 1982. (Box-folder 2:22)
- Presentation about Pacific Gas and Electric for a course (EM 245), 1982. (Box-folder 2:23)
- Project manual for the remodel of the garage shops building and enclosed storage--San Francisco service center, 1982. (Box-folder 2:24)
- Project manual for construction of Machine Shop expansion and Foreman's offices--Humbolt Bay power plant, 1982. (Box-folder 2:25)
- Project manual for construction of Hydro office expansion--Burney service center, 1982. (Box-folder 2:26)
- Slides of the San Francisco service center, 1982. (Box-folder 2:27)
- Scope of work for the proposed San Rafael service center, 1982. (Box-folder 2:28)
- Preliminary visual study and background report for proposed Healdsburg service center, 1982. (Box-folder 2:29)
- Photos of Humbolt Bay power plant machine shop remodeling, 1982. (Box-folder 2:30)
- Photos of Cascade district office, 1982. (Box-folder 2:31)
- Project manual for construction of machine shop expansion and Foreman's offices Humbolt Bay power plant, 1982. (Box-folder 2:32)
- Energy efficiency documents, 1982. (Box-folder 2:33)
- Slides of Coast Valleys division presentation, 1982. (Box-folder 2:34)
- Cascade district office--Slides, 1982. (Box-folder 2:35)
- Healdsburg service center--Slides, 1982. (Box-folder 2:36)
- Petawma office (old)--Photos and negatives, 1982. (Box-folder 2:37)
- Burney service center hydro-office extension--Photos, 1982. (Box-folder 2:38)
- Humbolt Bay power plant machine shop remodel--Photos, 1982. (Box-folder 2:39)
- Cascade district office--Photos and negatives, 1982. (Box-folder 2:40)
- Articles about Beverly Willis, 1982-83. (Box-folder 3:1)
- Slides of San Francisco division and district relocation, 1982-83. (Box-folder 3:2)
- Information for construction in Bodega Bay, California, 1982-83. (Box-folder 3:3)
- Documents concerning firesprinklers in the Western Addition Cultural Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:4)
- Town School for Boys' "Fun Run" paperwork, 1983. (Box-folder 3:5)
- Proposal from Willis and Associates Inc. for architectural services for the East Geysers Administration Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:6)
- Proposal from MBT Associates for architectural services for the East Geysers Administration Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:7)
- Proposal from Roland/Miller/Associates for architectural services for the East Geysers Administration Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:8)
- Proposal from Pflueger Architects for architectural services for the East Geysers Administration Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Project manual for the site work construction for the Geysers Administration Center and the Satellite Administration Center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:10)
- San Francisco division A.C.D.S. unit--slide presentation, 1983. (Box-folder 3:11)
- Specification for site preparation, road realignment, and related work for Geysers Satellite service center at Geysers power plant, 1983. (Box-folder 3:12)
- Photos and negatives of Geysers Satellite servic center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:13)
- Cruise's resume, 1983. (Box-folder 3:14)
- New furniture, 1983. (Box-folder 3:15)
- Pacific Gas and Electric East Geysers Administration Center Architectural Program--Sonoma County, California, 1983. (Box-folder 3:16)
- Pacific Gas and Electric East Geysers Administration Center Interview notes--Sonoma County, California, 1983. (Box-folder 3:17)
- Slides of Burney service center, 1983. (Box-folder 3:18)
- Slides of Petaluma office opening, 1983. (Box-folder 3:19)
- Slides of East Geysers Administration Center grading, 1983. (Box-folder 3:20)
- Pacific Gas and Electric Energy management manual, 1983. (Box-folder 3:21)
- Cascade district service center--Job estimate, 1984. (Box-folder 3:22)
- Work done for Sharon Lindeman, 1984. (Box-folder 3:23)
- Biographical Information, 1984. (Box-folder 3:24)
- Economic feasibility study--Customer service office for Garberville, 1984. (Box-folder 3:25)
- San Bruno office--Photos, 1984. (Box-folder 3:26)
- Tutorial on CADD in the building process, 1984. (Box-folder 3:27)
- Tutorial on effective CADD administrative management techniques, 1984. (Box-folder 3:28)
- Tutorial on effective CADD production management techniques, 1984. (Box-folder 3:29)
- Tutorial on CAE and the design process: the use of 3-dimensional graphics, 1984. (Box-folder 3:30)
- Proposal from CH2M Hill for architectural and engineering services for the Cascade service center, 1984. (Box-folder 3:31)
- Project manual for the East Geysers Administration Center, 1984. (Box-folder 3:32)
- Building department conference--Preparation of job estimates, 1984. (Box-folder 3:33)
- North Bay division--Geyserville service center study, 1984. (Box-folder 3:34)
- San Rafael service center specifications, 1984. (Box-folder 3:35)
- Specification for phase II remodelin of the San Francisco service center, 1984. (Box-folder 4:1)
- Request for proposal for architectural/engineering services for the Cascade service center, 1984. (Box-folder 4:2)
- Proposal from Pflueger Architects for San Francisco service center master plan, 1985. (Box-folder 4:3)
- Leased office facilities, 1985. (Box-folder 4:4)
- Cross-section of management women luncheons, 1985-86. (Box-folder 4:5)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan--Volume 1, 1986. (Box-folder 4:6)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan--Volume 2, 1986. (Box-folder 4:7)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan--Volume 3, 1986. (Box-folder 4:8)
- Phased Developmental Master Plan for San Francisco division-- phase I report, 1986. (Box-folder 4:9)
- Specification for underground transmission storage facility--Martin substation, 1986. (Box-folder 4:10)
- Proposal from ROMA Design Group for the San Francisco service center master plan, 1986. (Box-folder 4:11)
- Traffic master plan final report for San Francisco division consolidation project, 1986. (Box-folder 4:12)
- Phase I report on San Francisco division master plan, 1986. (Box-folder 4:13)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant--I+C/Telecommunications/Medical facility, 1987. (Box-folder 4:14)
- Note and old photo of Geyserville service center site, 1987. (Box-folder 4:15)
- California Architect Licensing Exam, 1987. (Box-folder 4:16)
- Notice of job opportunity as Senior Architect with the County of San Francisco, 1987. (Box-folder 4:17)
- Group leader responsibilities, 1987-88. (Box-folder 4:18)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant I+C/Telecommunications/Medical facility plans and specifications, 1988. (Box-folder 4:19)
- Request for proposal for design and construction services of the liquid storage warehouse and gas cylinder storage structure--Diablo Canyon Power Plant, 1988. (Box-folder 4:20)
- Specifications for the Second floor of the Administration building-- Diablo Canyon Power Plant, 1988. (Box-folder 4:21)
- Revisions of the Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan-- Volume 1, 1988. (Box-folder 4:22)
- Revisions of the Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan-- Volume 2, 1988. (Box-folder 4:23)
- Revisions of the Diablo Canyon Power Plant site master plan-- Volume 3, 1988. (Box-folder 4:24)
- OWA Mid-Career Retreat, 1989. (Box-folder 5:1)
- Design changes for Diablo Canyon Power Plant, 1989. (Box-folder 5:2)
- Nuclear power systems training guide (folder 1 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:3)
- Nuclear power systems training guide (folder 2 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:4)
- Nuclear power systems training guide (folder 3 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:5)
- Nuclear power systems training guide (folder 4 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:6)
- Design Criteria memorandum for a document storage facility at the Diablo Canyon Power Plant, 1989. (Box-folder 5:7)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant Intake structure maintenance facility, 1989. (Box-folder 5:8)
- Nuclear engineering manual training handout, 1989. (Box-folder 5:9)
- Nuclear power plant systems manual (folder 1 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:10)
- Nuclear power plant systems manual (folder 2 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:11)
- Nuclear power plant systems manual (folder 3 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:12)
- Nuclear power plant systems manual (folder 4 of 4), 1989. (Box-folder 5:13)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant monthly status reports (folder 1 of 3), 1989-90. (Box-folder 5:14)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant monthly status reports (folder 2 of 3), 1989-90. (Box-folder 5:15)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant monthly status reports (folder 3 of 3), 1989-90. (Box-folder 5:16)
- Specification for containment coatings--Diablo Canyon Power Plant, 1990. (Box-folder 5:17)
- Customer Technology Center manual, 1990. (Box-folder 5:18)
- Potential user's interest in Pacific Gas and Electric commercial lighting center, 1990. (Box-folder 5:19)
- Nuclear power generation--Business Plan, 1990-94. (Box-folder 6:1)
- Project manual for the Customer Technology Center, 1991. (Box-folder 6:2)
- October progress report for the Pacific Energy Center, 1991. (Box-folder 6:3)
- Pacific Energy Center project folder (folder 1 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:4)
- Pacific Energy Center project folder (folder 2 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:5)
- Pacific Energy Center project folder (folder 3 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:6)
- Pacific Energy Center project development report (folder 1 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:7)
- Pacific Energy Center project development report (folder 2 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:8)
- Pacific Energy Center project development report (folder 3 of 3), 1991. (Box-folder 6:9)
- Pacific Energy Center education opportunities, 1991. (Box-folder 6:10)
- Pacific Energy Center grand opening media coverage, 1991. (Box-folder 6:11)
- Pacific Energy Center opening day television spots, 1991. (Box-folder 6:12)
- Building permit for the Customer Technology Center's energy efficiency offices, 1991. (Box-folder 6:13)
- Pacific Gas and Electric energy efficiency services memoranda, 1992. (Box-folder 6:14)
- 5th annual California Women in Environmental Design conference-- Santa Monica, California, 1992. (Box-folder 6:15)
- "The Energy Challenge" Video, 1992. (Box-folder 6:16)
- Information about Presidio of San Francisco, 1992-93. (Box-folder 6:17)
- Proposals to perform the annual audit for the San Francisco chapter of the AIA, 1993. (Box-folder 6:18)
- Memos and letters about the AIA Board of Directors (folder 1 of 3), 1993. (Box-folder 7:1)
- Memos and letters about the AIA Board of Directors (folder 2 of 3), 1993. (Box-folder 7:2)
- Memos and letters about the AIA Board of Directors (folder 3 of 3), 1993. (Box-folder 7:3)
- Literature from the 6th annual California Women in Environmental Design conference--San Diego, California, 1993. (Box-folder 7:4)
- "Design=Leadership" a California Women in Environmental Design publication, 1993. (Box-folder 7:5)
- Earth Day address by President Bill Clinton, 1993. (Box-folder 7:6)
- Documents of the AIA San Francisco chapter, 1994. (Box-folder 7:7)
- National Institute of Standards and Technology's Green Building conference itenerary--Gaithersburg, Maryland, 1994. (Box-folder 7:8)
- Energy Retrofit program report--Stanford University Utilities department, 1994. (Box-folder 7:9)
- AIA California council board book, 1995. (Box-folder 7:10)
- Miscellaneous photos, n.d. (Box-folder 7:11)
- Video titled "Trade Ally Connection", n.d. (Box-folder 7:12)
- Awards and accolades, n.d. (Box-folder 7:13)
- Job descriptions for Pacific Gas and Electric, n.d. (Box-folder 7:14)
- Resumes of Cruise, n.d. (Box-folder 7:15)
- Personnel folder of Cruise, n.d. (Box-folder 7:16)
- Cruise's company stationary and business cards, n.d. (Box-folder 7:17)
- Personalized stationary and business cards from Pacific Gas and Electric, n.d. (Box-folder 7:18)
- Rendering of the Cascade district office, n.d. (Box-folder 7:19)
- Tape measure from Pacific Gas and Electric, n.d. (Box-folder 7:20)
- "Planning and Scheduling Made Easy"--seminar by Battelle Pacific Northwest Laboratories, n.d. (Box-folder 7:21)
- Napa office--photos, n.d. (Box-folder 7:22)
- East Geysers model photos, n.d. (Box-folder 7:23)
- Potrero power plant women's washroom--Photos and negatives, n.d. (Box-folder 7:24)
- Miscellaneous photos and negatives, n.d. (Box-folder 7:25)
- Potrero power plant women's locker room--Photos and negatives, n.d. (Box-folder 7:26)
- Slides of East Geysers service center, n.d. (Box-folder 7:27)
- Garberville slide presentation, n.d. (Box-folder 7:28)
- Photo of Cruise, n.d. (Box-folder 7:29)
- Biographical Information, 2001. (Box-folder 7:30)
- Contract documents for the construction of Southeast Water Pollution Control Plant expansion, 1977. (Flatbox-folder 1:1)
- Model of the Shasta/Cascade office, 1980. (Flatbox-folder 1:2)
- Transparencies for a blueprint reading class taught by Cruise, 1981. (Flatbox-folder 1:3)
- Cascade district office drawings, 1981. (Flatbox-folder 1:4)
- Diablo Canyon Power Plant--I&C/Telecommunications/Medical facility drawings, 1988. (Flatbox-folder 1:5)
- Miscellaneous photo, n.d. (Flatbox-folder 1:6)
- Maine Avenue Apartments (1 drawing), 1967. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Alterations of the Junior Academy and Docent offices of the California Academy of Sciences (14 drawings), 1977-78. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Second floor of the Administration building--Diablo Canyon Power Plant (39 drawings), 1985-88. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Liquid Storage Warehouse--Diablo Canyon Power Plant (15 drawings), 1986-88. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- I&C/Telecommunications/Medical facility--Diablo Canyon Power Plant (17 drawings), 1988. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Turbine Generator Equipment Warehouse--Diablo Canyon Power Plant (5 drawings), 1988. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Sandblast and Spray Paint facility--Diablo Canyon Power Plant (25 drawings), 1989. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Buchanan House Apartments(2 drawings), n.d. (Folder 1 (Oversize))
- Proposed Neal Residence (1 drawing), n.d. (Folder 1 (Oversize))